Veterinary World UP104
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Veterinary World
1986 -- 1999
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Cummings School of Veterinary Medicine
UP104
0.55 Linear Feet
1 Volumes
210.9 Megabytes 36 PDFs
This collection contains issues of Veterinary World, a publication of the Cummings School of Veterinary Medicine, Tufts University.
Arrangement
This collection is organized chronologically in one series.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains issues of Veterinary World. It is a newsletter of School Veterinary Medicine faculty, staff, students, alumni, events, and programs. It is published three times a year as a progress report of Tufts University School of Veterinary Medicine and is distributed to university personnel, veterinary students, veterinarians, alumni, and other interested parties. It covers stories relating to the school, medical developments, and alumni. Its predecessor was Tufts Veterinary News (UP176).
Related Materials
UP176, Tufts Veterinary News, DCA
Biographical / Historical
The School of Veterinary Medicine was established in 1978, opened in 1979, and graduated its first class in 1983. Established through the advocacy of President Jean Mayer, the school was unique in its affiliation to a health sciences complex rather than to a school of agriculture. The school is located on a 634 acre campus in Grafton, Massachusetts, site of a former state mental hospital. The school also shares facilities with the medical and dental schools on the downtown Boston campus, where vet students receive their first year of instruction in the basic sciences. Students at the veterinary school are exposed to care of all types of animals including food (cattle, sheep, swine, goat), fiber (sheep, llama), companion (dog, cat), and sporting (horse) animals. In addition, students are given the option of learning about care for wildlife through the wildlife medicine program. In addition to medicine, surgery, preventive medicine, and public health, the school also educates students about ethics, conservation medicine, and human-animal relationships.
Initial discussions on the establishment of a veterinary school were begun in the early 1970s as the absence of such a school in the New England region combined with a prediction of a nationwide deficit of veterinarians made the need apparent. After a variety of options were explored, including locating a school at the Otis Air Force base on Cape Cod, Tufts, under Jean Mayer's leadership, stepped forward to take the lead in the project. Richard B. Talbot, dean of the College of Veterinary Medicine at Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University was brought in as interim dean to oversee the startup of the school on a part-time basis. On April 29, 1978, the trustees voted to establish the school as part of Mayer's vision of an integrated "one medicine" program embracing the totality of medical, dental, veterinary, and nutrition education.
The school provides clinical facilities as part of the Tufts-New England Veterinary Medical Center, which includes the Foster Hospital for Small Animals, the Large Animal Hospital, the Cornelius Thibeault Equine Clinic, the Amelia Peabody Pavilion, the Issam Fares Equine Sports Medicine Program, the Harrington Oncology Program, and the Wildlife Clinic at Grafton, as well as the Marine Biological Laboratory at Woods Hole, and the Ambulatory Farm Clinic based at Woodstock, Connecticut.
The degree of Doctor of Veterinary Medicine (D.V.M.) is the primary degree offered by the school, though since 1995 the school also offers a Master of Science (M.S.) in Animals and Public Policy. The school features several signature programs which offer specialized perspectives on veterinary sciences, including Wildlife Medicine, Equine Sports Medicine, International Veterinary Medicine, Ethics and Values in Veterinary Medicine, and Biotechnology and Veterinary Medicine.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Digital material was transferred by the Webster Family Library, Cummings School of Veterinary Medicine, Tufts University, 2019, accession UA-2020-014.
- Veterinary World, 1986 -- 1999; UP104.001; 0.55 Linear Feet; 1 Volumes
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains issues of Veterinary World which is published three times a year as a newsletter of School of Veterinary Medicine faculty, staff, students, alumni, events, and programs. It is distributed to university personnel, veterinary students, veterinarians, alumni and other interested parties. It covers stories relating to the school, medical developments and alumni. Its predecessor was Tufts Veterinary News (UP176).
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged chronologically.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - Veterinary World, 1986; UP104.001.001.00001 (Box 1)
  - Veterinary World, Summer 1986; UP104.000019; 4.95 Megabytes
  - Veterinary World, Winter 1986 -- 1987; UP104.000020; 5.65 Megabytes
  - Veterinary World, 1987; UP104.001.001.00002 (Box 1)
  - Veterinary World, Summer 1987; UP104.000021; 5.11 Megabytes
  - Veterinary World, Winter 1987 -- 1988; UP104.000022; 5.07 Megabytes
  - Veterinary World, 1988; UP104.001.001.00003 (Box 1)
  - Veterinary World, Spring -- Summer 1988; UP104.000023; 6.86 Megabytes
  - Veterinary World, Fall 1988; UP104.000024; 10.83 Megabytes
  - Veterinary World, 1989; UP104.001.001.00004 (Box 1)
  - Veterinary World, Spring 1989; UP104.000025; 6.7 Megabytes
  - Veterinary World, Summer 1989; UP104.000026; 5.4 Megabytes
  - Veterinary World, Winter 1989 -- 1990; UP104.000027; 7.2 Megabytes
  - Veterinary World, Spring 1990; UP104.000028; 7.2 Megabytes
  - Veterinary World, Fall 1990; UP104.000029; 7.07 Megabytes
  - Veterinary World, Winter 1990 -- 1991; UP104.000030; 5.4 Megabytes
  - Veterinary World, 1991; UP104.001.001.00005 (Box 1)
  - Veterinary World, Spring 1991; UP104.000031; 7.19 Megabytes
  - Veterinary World, Fall 1991; UP104.000032; 7.25 Megabytes
  - Veterinary World, 1992; UP104.001.001.00007 (Box 1)
  - Veterinary World, Spring 1992; UP104.000033; 8.73 Megabytes
  - Veterinary World, Fall 1992; UP104.000034; 5.08 Megabytes
  - Veterinary World, 1993; UP104.001.001.00008 (Box 1)
  - Veterinary World, Winter 1993; UP104.000035; 5.04 Megabytes
  - Veterinary World, Spring 1993; UP104.000036; 5.21 Megabytes
  - Veterinary World, Fall 1993; UP104.000037; 8.72 Megabytes
  - Veterinary World, 1994; UP104.001.001.00009 (Box 1)
  - Veterinary World, Winter 1994; UP104.000038; 5.11 Megabytes
  - Veterinary World, Spring 1994; UP104.000039; 5.35 Megabytes
  - Veterinary World, Fall 1994; UP104.000040; 5.49 Megabytes
  - Veterinary World, 1995; UP104.001.001.00006 (Box 1)
  - Veterinary World, Spring 1995; UP104.000041; 5.22 Megabytes
  - Veterinary World, Fall 1995; UP104.000042; 4.71 Megabytes
  - Veterinary World, Winter 1995 -- 1996; UP104.000043; 5.21 Megabytes
  - Veterinary World, Spring 1996; UP104.000044; 5 Megabytes
  - Veterinary World, Fall 1996; UP104.000045; 5.04 Megabytes
  - Veterinary World, Winter 1996 -- 1997; UP104.000046; 4.71 Megabytes
  - Veterinary World, Spring 1997; UP104.000047; 4.58 Megabytes
  - Veterinary World, Fall, 1997; UP104.001.002.00001 (Box Volume 2)
  - Veterinary World, Winter, 1997 -- 1998; UP104.001.002.00002 (Box Volume 2)
  - Veterinary World, Spring, 1998; UP104.001.002.00003 (Box Volume 2)
  - Veterinary World, Fall, 1998; UP104.001.002.00004 (Box Volume 2)
  - Veterinary World, Winter, 1999; UP104.001.002.00005 (Box Volume 2)
  - Veterinary World, Spring, 1999; UP104.001.002.00006 (Box Volume 2)
  - Veterinary World, Summer, 1999; UP104.001.002.00007 (Box Volume 2)